Register of the Leon Mitkiewicz Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Leon Mitkiewicz papers,
1918-1969
65001
Mitkiewicz, Leon
10 manuscript boxes (4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Diary, correspondence, writings, and printed matter, relating to Polish foreign relations with Russia, Czechoslovakia, the Baltic States, and other countries, 1914-1944; the Warsaw uprising of August 1944; and World War II Allied diplomacy.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (11 reels).
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/ to find the full extent of the collection.
Biographical Note
1896 Born, Zambrow, Poland
1914-1917 Cavalry officer, Russian Army
1918-1921 2nd Legion Infantry Division
1921 General Staff, 2nd Lancers Regiment
1925 General Staff Academy graduate
1925-1935 War Academy lecturer, Field service
1935-1938 Chief of Staff Army Inspectorate
1938-1939 Military attaché, Kaunas, Lithuania
1940-1941 General Staff member Chief of Second Intelligence Bureau
1943 Deputy Commander, 1st Army Division
1943-1945 Polish Military Mission, Combined Chiefs of Staff, Washington
1972 Died, New York
Scope and Content Note
Leon Mitkiewicz's papers are a unique source of documentation for scholars studying World War II, as they bear testimony to his knowledge of and expertise in the history of 20th century Poland. They relate mainly to his twenty-five yearlong military service as a high rank officer in Poland's General Staff and as a military attaché to both Lithuania and the United States. Of particular significance are his duties in the Polish Military Mission in Washington until its liquidation in 1945, which are documented in the biographical file.
In the post-war years, Mitkiewicz devoted himself to writing. Having witnessed some of the most important events of the century, he left excellent descriptions of their unfolding; they constitute the core of this collection.
These papers are supplemented by many other collections from the same period housed at the Hoover Institution, such as the papers of Wladyslaw Anders and Izydor Modelski, and the records of Poland. Ambasada (United States) and Poland. Ministerstwo Spraw Zagranicznych, to mention but a few.
The Mitkiewicz collection was acquired by the Hoover Institution in 1974. A large portion of his papers is also housed at the Sikorski Institute in London.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; World War, 1939-1945--Poland.; Baltic States.; Baltic States--Foreign relations--Poland.; Czechoslovakia.; Czechoslovakia--Foreign relations--Poland.; Poland.; Poland--Foreign relations--Baltic States.; Poland--Foreign relations--Czechoslovakia.; Poland--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Poland--History--20th century.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--Foreign relations--Poland.; Warsaw (Poland)--History--Uprising, 1944.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1945-1976. (Box 1)
  Correspondence, clippings, notes, typescripts documenting the life and career of Leon Mitkiewicz, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Correspondence, 1939-1958. (Box 1)
  Letters arranged alphabetically by name of corespondent
- Diary, 1942. (Box 1)
  Typescript
- Subject File, 1933-1945. (Box 1-2)
  Correspondence, clippings, memoranda, minutes of meetings, reports, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Writings, 1943-1967. (Box 3-10)
  Typescripts, notes, and clippings relating to Mitkiewicz's military career, particularly when he was a military attaché and to his relationship with General Sikorski; Polish military action against Czechoslovakia; the Wars of 1920-1921 with Russia; the Warsaw Uprising, 1944; and Poland's relations with Russia, Lithuania, and Germany; arranged chronologically by title
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1945-1976 (Box 1)
  - General
    - General (Folder 1: 1)
    - Invitations (Folder 1: 2)
    - Photostats (Folder 1: 3)
    - Stationery (Folder 1: 4)
  - Career and military service., See also SUBJECT FILE/ Combined Chiefs of Staff (U.S. and Great Britain) and Intelligence services - Poland
    - General (Folder 1: 5)
    - Polish Military Mission in the United States, 1945 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Childhood (Folder 1: 7)
  - Mitkiewiczowa, Stefania (Folder 1: 8)
  - Press, 1970-1971
    - General (Folder 1: 9)
    - Placowka Star (Folder 1: 10)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1939-1958
  - Arnold, H. H., 1944 (Folder 1: 11)
  - Bellona, 1943 (Folder 1: 12)
  - Biddle, Anthony, 1941-1942 (Folder 1: 13)
  - Bissel, Clayton, 1944 (Folder 1: 14)
  - Charwat, Franciszek, 1939 (Folder 1: 15)
  - Clarke, A. W., 1941 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Coleridge, R. D., 1944 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Cornwall, Marshall, 1940 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Davidson, Major, 1941-1942 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Davis, Donald, 1945 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Dill, J. G., 1943-1944 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Gibson, A., 1949 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Giedroyc, Jerzy, 1958., See also BIOGRAPHICAL FILE/Press (Folder 1: 23)
  - Kelly, W. D., 1949 (Folder 1: 24)
  - King, E. J., 1944 (Folder 1: 25)
  - Klimecki, Tadeusz, 1942 (Folder 1: 26)
  - Kopanski, Stanislaw, 1944 (Folder 1: 27)
  - Kukiel, M., 1943 (Folder 1: 28)
  - Leahy, William, D., 1943-1945 (Folder 1: 29)
  - Lodd, Virginia, 1943 (Folder 1: 30)
  - Lubienski, Ludwik, 1943 (Folder 1: 31)
  - Macready, G. N., 1944 (Folder 1: 32)
  - Marshall, George C., 1944 (Folder 1: 33)
  - Molloy, P. G., 1947 (Folder 1: 34)
  - Onacewicz, Wlodzimierz, 1943 (Folder 1: 35)
  - Roberts-McCoy, Clare, 1944 (Folder 1: 36)
  - Rowan, Colonel, 1942 (Folder 1: 37)
  - Sosnkowski, Kazimierz, 1944 (Folder 1: 38)
  - Timesdell, S., 1944 (Folder 1: 39)
  - Wierzynski, Kazimierz, 1944 (Folder 1: 40)
- DIARY, 1942 April 21 - May 14. (Folder 1: 41)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1933-1945 (Box 1-2)
  - Beck, Jozef, "Preliminacje polityczne do wojny 1939," letter to Wieniawa-Dlugoszowski, 1940 (Folder 1: 42)
  - Cavalry - Poland, 1933 (Folder 1: 43)
  - Cieszyn Region, 1938-1946 (Folder 1: 44)
  - Combined Chiefs of Staff (U.S. and Great Britain)
    - 1943 (Folder 1: 45)
    - 1944 (Folder 1: 46)
    - 1945 (Folder 1: 47)
  - Germany - Military policy. Field service regulations, 1930 (Box-folder 2: 1)
  - Intelligence services - Poland
    - General
      - 1939 (Folder 2: 2)
      - 1940 (Folder 2: 3)
      - 1941 (Folder 2: 4)
      - 1942 (Folder 2: 5)
      - 1943 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Reports
      - 1941 (Folder 2: 7)
      - 1942 (Folder 2: 8)
      - 1943 (Folder 2: 9)
      - 1945 (Folder 2: 10)
      - 1946 (Folder 2: 11)
  - Pilsudski, Jozef - Funeral, 1935 (Folder 2: 12)
  - Sikorski, Wladyslaw - Airplane accidents, 1942-1943
    - General (Folder 2: 13)
    - Polish-American press (Folder 2: 14)
  - Slaski, Eugeniusz, 1963 (Folder 2: 15)
  - World War, 1939-1945
    - September 1939 campaign
      - General (Folder 2: 16)
      - Bzura battle, 1939 (Folder 2: 17)
    - Warsaw Uprising, 1944. (Folder 2: 18)
      Materials relating to the Polish military efforts in the United States on behalf of the Warsaw Uprising
- WRITINGS, 1943-1967
  - "Trzy Wizyty Generala Wladyslawa Sikorskiego do Stanow Zjednoczonych, 1941-1942," 1943-1944.
    - Part I, "Pierwsza wizyta, Marzec-Maj, 1941" (Folder 2: 19)
    - Part II, "Zalacznik no. 2" (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Part III, "Zalacznik no. 5" (Folder 3: 2)
  - "Na Obczyznie z Generalem Wladyslawem Sikorskim. Wspomnienia Wojenne z Lat 1940-1943," 1946.
    - Chapters
      - 1-4 (Folder 3: 3)
      - 5-7 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Enclosures (Folder 3: 5)
  - "Powstanie Warszawskie w Sierpniu 1944 Roku w Swietle Dokumentow Polskiej Misji Wojskowej w Stanach Zjednoczonych," 1953.
    - Copy 1 (Folder 3: 6)
    - Copy 2 (Box-folder 4: 1)
    - Copy 3 (Folder 4: 2)
  - "Polska Akcja Przeciwko Czechoslowacji Celem Odzyskania Slaska Zaolzianskiego w Jesieni 1938 roku," 1954. (Folder 4: 3)
  - "Litwa i Polska Pomiedzy Dwoma Wojnami Swiatowymi, 1914-1939," 1955. (Folder 4: 4)
  - "Wspomnienia Kowienskie, 1938-1939," 1956.
    - Copy 1 (Folder 4: 5)
    - Copy 2 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - Copy 3 (Folder 5: 2)
  - "Odwieczna Polityka Rosyjska Wzgledem Rzczypospolitej Polskiej," 1956-1958. (Box 6)
    Typescript in Polish and English
    - Part I (Folder 6: 1)
    - Part II (Folder 6: 2)
    - Part III (Folder 6: 3)
    - Part IV (Box-folder 7: 1)
    - Part V (Folder 7: 2)
  - "Kawaleria Samodzielna Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej w Wojnie 1939 Roku," 1961
    - Research material
      - Clippings (Folder 7: 3)
      - Notes (Folder 7: 4)
    - Typescript (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - "W Najwyzszym Dowodztwie Aliantow. Wspomnienia Wojenne, 1943-1945," 1962. (Folder 8: 2)
  - "W Najwyzszym Sztabie Zachodnich Aliantow. Wspomnienia Wojenne, 1943-1945," 1962. (Folder 8: 3)
  - "W Wojsku Rzeczypospolitej Polskiej w Czasie Wojen 1917-1921," 1967. (Box 9)
    - Copy 1
      - Part I (Folder 9: 1)
      - Part II (Folder 9: 2)
      - Part III (Folder 9: 3)
    - Copy 2
      - Part I (Folder 9: 4)
      - Part II (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - "Z Brzekiem Ostrog i z Dzwiekiem Szabli," 1967.
    - Part I (Folder 10: 2)
    - Part II (Folder 10: 3)
    - Part III (Folder 10: 4)